Just a few days ago, on 31st December 2025,
my mother's elbow got fractured.
A small accident occurs resulting in a
fracture.  And when this fracture
occurs, the pain is very severe.
We rush to the hospital.  You are
admitted to the hospital and
after admission the hospital staff
asks you whether you have any insurance?  So
we said we have insurance, so
he asks us for the insurance papers.  So I have
taken two insurances for my mother and
both are from the same company.  I
will tell you why I have taken it now.  So in one insurance there is a
sum assured of Rs 5 lakh.  Look, I have
opened it here also.  My mother's name is
Baby Sinha.  The second insurance is also the same.
Look here, this is a sum assured of Rs 50 lakh.
This is also in my mother's name.  So when a
person is in a hurry, his mind is not working at that time.
So I have an
insurance that I see
comes to me first on email.  I
hand him that document.  Ok?  So that
document was for insurance of Rs 5 lakh.
I handed him the document.
So the mother stays in the hospital for about three to four days.
After that discharge takes place.   At the
time of discharge, the bill is generated for ₹3,60,000
and the accountant tells me that
only ₹5 lakh has been
approved from your insurance.  You will have to pay around ₹1 lakh
from your pocket.  I said
why should I pay from my pocket?  That
insurance is worth Rs 50 lakh.  So the accountant
says it is not worth Rs 50 lakh.  Your
insurance is only for Rs 5 lakh.  Then I
checked and accidentally found out that
I had given him the old insurance paper
which was running.  I have
also continued this insurance.
I have continued this also.  Actually there are
two insurances because look, I had taken
insurance in 2019.  So in 2019
we took insurance of ₹5 lakh.  At that
time, I also did not understand much about
what to look for and what not to look for in insurance.
Because of this I made a big
mistake.  I will tell you about that mistake also.  Now he had
taken insurance of Rs 5 lakh.  So just
some time ago we realized that Rs 5 lakh is
too less for mom.  So now we have
taken insurance of ₹ lakh.  And we have
taken this very recently.
I pay ₹68,000 for this ₹50 lakh insurance
and
I pay ₹25,000 as premium for this ₹5 lakh insurance.  I have kept
both of them running.
Now the accountant tells me that yours is worth Rs 5
lakh.  So I realized that it was my mistake
brother, I had given the one worth Rs 5 lakh.  But
just think, if I have
given insurance papers of Rs 5 lakh then
why is there approval for Rs 5 lakh?  The bill is approximately for ₹3.5 lakh, so the
entire ₹3.5 lakh should be covered in this 5 lakh.  Should it happen
or not
?
So why is that accountant saying that
you will get only ₹5 lakh?  The remaining Rs 1 lakh will
not be received.  It is something to think about.  Even though
I have given Rs 5 lakh, brother.  There
is a cover of Rs 5 lakh also.  There is also a policy sum of Rs 5 lakh.
So ₹5 lakh should be given to the hospital.  Should have
given it to the insurance company.
Why should I pay?
But I had to pay ₹1 lakh.  Although I did
not have to pay.  Because I had another
insurance, I took the remaining Rs 1 lakh from it.
But just imagine,
if this new one was not worth Rs 50 lakh, then
despite having an insurance of Rs 5 lakh, I would have had to
pay Rs 1 lakh from my pocket.  Why?
Sir, because I also did not check while taking this policy.  There is a
copay in this policy.
You will say what is copay?
Copay is a feature of any health
insurance policy and by default it is
included in many policies.
If you don't see it, it will cause you harm.
When will he cause harm?  When you face such a
situation of hospitalization, then
you will realize that brother was involved.  I didn't know, I hadn't
seen it.  So what is this copy,
I will explain it to you in detail now and
along with that there are eight-nine more things which if
you do not see then
you will keep paying your health insurance premium for years
but when you get admitted in the hospital and at the
time of discharge, now it is the
turn of the patient to go home, at that time the
hospital person will tell you that even though your insurance is
of 10 lakhs, even though the bill is of 7 lakhs,
but you will have to pay 3 lakhs from your pocket, the
insurance is of 10 lakhs.  The bill has
come for only Rs 7 lakh.  But why should I have to pay Rs 3 lakh from my pocket
?  Brother, there are eight to nine such
different factors.  If you do not pay attention,
most of the people do
not pay attention to all these factors while taking health insurance,
due to which despite having insurance, they have to
pay money from their pocket.  So that all those
factors come into play.  I will explain it to you today.
Look, at least one screenshot is left.  Had to
show a screenshot.  Look, this
SMS has come that there is approval of Rs 2.5 lakh.
Look, at the time of discharge,
approval of Rs 2.5 lakh has come for Baby Sena.  This is from Monday only.
So I showed you all the screenshots so that
you know that this is a
genuine case brother.  Ok?
So now the question arises, what is that copay
and what are those seven, eight, nine factors that
we must look at while taking health insurance.
Otherwise, you are sure to be cut.  You won't even know.
Sir, no one will tell you that
you did not consider this thing while taking health insurance.
Keep paying the premium.  We will know
when it is time for hospitalization.   We will know
then.  So today let me explain this to you in detail.
Now let's come to the main
issue.  Now let us understand
what are all those points which
anyone should keep in mind while taking health insurance.
Otherwise this will definitely happen to you
brother.  sure will.
Keep paying the insurance premium but you will still have to pay from your pocket.
Now what are those pointers
?  Please understand carefully.  The first
pointer is the room rent limit.
People see that brother, we have got a room rent limit of
₹5,000 per day.  Meaning,
when you or anyone else in the house gets hospitalized,
God forbid, there may be a need for hospitalization, but
whenever it happens, it is written in your policy
that the insurance company will pay ₹5000 per day for the room
rent. You say that it will pay ₹5000. ₹5000 room
rent is okay friend, it is not much, okay we will manage it
for ₹000 and if ever we have to pay more,
₹3000, then we will pay from our pocket,
what is the problem in that, the room rent
is less, everything else is fine, but what happens because of this,
Sir, suppose you have taken a
room which has a rent.
Nowadays, even hospitals have become hotels.
If you go to big hospitals,
brother, money is taken in the name of the same facilities.
Suppose the actual rent of the room was
₹10,000.  Your insurance company cover was
only ₹5,000.  You say it is ₹5,000
extra.  I have to stay in the hospital for three days.  I will
pay ₹15,000 extra from my pocket.
What difference does it make?
But that won't happen, sir.  will what?  If the
total bill of the entire hospital is ₹1 lakh,
then the company will give you only ₹5 lakh.   Will
not give 5 lakhs.  Now ask why?  I suffered a
loss of Rs 5 lakh.  Despite having insurance of Rs 10 lakh.
Why?  Because sir, if
you have taken a room double the room rent limit,
then your insurance
also gets levied.  Did you understand what I said?
Understand what I am saying.  If you said that
room rent of Rs 5,000 is covered in your insurance.
You took 10,000.  This means that if you take double room,
you will get only half of your total room bill.  What happens is that not just the
room but the entire bill gets halved.   There will be
proportionate deduction brother.
Nine out of 10 people don't know this.  They
see that the room rent is low.  No problem.  I will
pay from my pocket.  Room rent has to be
paid.  Sir, according to that the bill also gets halved.
So a bill of Rs 10 lakh will fetch Rs 5 lakh.
So look for such a policy in which there is no room rent
limit at all. There should not be any room rent limit because
because of that the policy gets completely messed up.
Either there should be no room rent limit or it should be
1% of the total sum assured.  You get two types of options.
Either there is no ROM rent
or the sum assured is 1% of the total policy.
What I mean to say is that now suppose you have a policy of Rs 10 lakh, then
1% of the policy of Rs 10 lakh becomes
your ROM rent limit i.e. Rs 10,000.  And
it keeps increasing later.  I
will tell you later how it grows.  I will come in a while.
And for availing this no room rent limit,
you have to pay an extra premium of only ₹3,000 annually.
To save this money, a person takes a room rent cap
policy which has a room rent limit.  So keep in mind that there should not be any room rent
limit in your policy or there should be
1% off sum.  Don't make this mistake in the first place.
Second, family floater or
individual.  There are two types of health insurance
policies.  A family floater.  Family
follow-up policy means that you take a policy in which
all the members of the family are covered.  The
second one is individual.   A
separate policy has been purchased for each family member.
Generally, what happens in a family floater is
that the husband, wife and children are covered
and the family floater is good for them also.
But what do we do sometimes
?  We also include parents.
In that family floater.  We should
not include parents at all.   A
separate policy should be taken for parents.
Like I have taken a
separate policy for parents.  Now you will say that he is
discriminating, friend, these are our parents, we should buy a
separate policy for them, sir. Emotional theories will
not work here,
understand it practically, what happens is that the parents are older,
they have more chances of falling sick, of getting some
kind of disease,
now what happens in that case is that
in the family floater, if your father gets
hospitalized, ₹1 lakh is spent there,
now after that only ₹1 lakh is left, if there
is a policy of 5 lakhs, 5 lakhs, then
after mother gets admitted, he has
only ₹1 lakh to pay to the hospital.   Any
bill above that will have to be paid from your own pocket.
So in this case, brother, keep the husband,
wife and children, whose
chances of getting hospitalized are less, in one package.
Put it in a family floater.
For those who have higher chances of getting hospitalized,
take a new policy.  Get a separate policy.  There should
always be a separate policy for parents as
they have higher chances of falling ill.
Yes, their premium is also high but
you will be saved from many things.  Is it okay
brother?  So the best strategy is that you yourself,
husband, wife and children should take a family floater.
After that, if the parents are above 50 years of age, then
definitely take a separate policy for them.  Ok?
My family floater which I have taken is worth Rs
1 crore.  Four people are
included in it.  Two children and husband and wife.   It is worth
₹1 crore.  I have kept aside Rs. 1 lakh of my mother's money.
I pay a premium of ₹68,000 for it.  68,000 is what
you showed, right?  Well, mine which is worth 1 crore
only goes towards premium of ₹00.  The
premium goes around Rs 505000.  But mom's is
only worth Rs 50 lakh, so she gets a premium of Rs 68,000.
Why?  The age has increased.  Ok
?  So did you understand the difference between family floater and individual
?
Now after that network hospitals.  Please
understand this carefully, sir.  What happens is that it is
written in the policy that
more than 10,000 network hospitals are covered.  This means
you will get cover in more than 10,000 hospitals.
But the question is,
how many hospitals in the city where you live are covered
in that policy?  What happens is that there is a policy
which covers 10,000 hospitals.
But
only two hospitals in the city where you live are covered under that policy.
Now there is another policy in which
only seven thousand hospital covers are written.
But 20 hospitals in your city
are covered under that policy.  Which policy is right?   The one
below.  Or
20 hospitals are covered in the city you live in.  Even though 7000
is written in that policy, it is better.
So you also have to see whether the
hospitals in the city where you are living are
covered in that policy or not.
This is something to be observed carefully.  You may find that there is
no cover in the policy for all the hospitals in your city.  So what is the
policy for now?  Well, no
one will tell you all this.  You will know this only when it is
time to take the policy cover.
When hospitalization occurs.  When you are
very thirsty, you will
not be able to dig a well, then the situation becomes something like this.  So that is why it is
very important to look at these parameters.  The parameter after that
is sumshard.  Many people wonder
how much policy should they take?  People say that a
health insurance policy of Rs 3 to 5 lakh is enough brother.  Hey, okay, a policy of ₹3 to ₹1
lakh is enough.  Look, in today's time,
if by mistake someone
needs to go to ICU, then the cost of ICU
is ₹30 to ₹00 per day.
If someone needs heart surgery, the
cost is ₹3 to ₹8 lakh.
If someone undergoes cancer treatment, a minimum of ₹5 to ₹1 lakh
is required.
If kidney transplant is to be done then it costs between ₹10 to ₹1 lakh.
Sir, look at these expenses, 3 to 5 lakhs, nowadays as soon as one
enters the hospital,
expenses are incurred on small things.  Last
year, I got my mother's
cataract operation done.
In small towns, cataract surgery costs between Rs 40 and Rs 500.  If you
go to a good hospital in a city like Delhi or Mumbai, it would
cost Rs 3 lakh.  In that too, a
small operation like cataract which takes a
few hours costs 3 to 5 lakhs, but think about
an operation which requires stay for three-four days, a
bill of 10, 12, 15 lakhs is generated in big cities like this,
cut cut cut cut cut cut, you will
not even know that it has become 10, 12, 15 lakhs, so that is why take
such a policy which is understandable brother, there should be enough
money that you can handle it, now the example is, there is
a Sharma ji whom we know, he
lives in Mumbai, he is 35 years old,
he was in ICU for five days and
his expenses amounted to 28 lakhs.  I am telling you a real case
study.  Surgery was done.
His expenses amounted to Rs 4 lakh.  The medicine and tests
that were done cost him Rs 1.5 lakh.
Post hospitalization, that is, the
cost of medicine and alcohol after leaving the hospital,
cost ₹1 lakh.
His total bill was ₹9 lakh.  Although all his
policies etc. were good.  The policy was worth ₹1 lakh
and he got ₹9 lakh.  But
think about it, if he had an insurance of Rs 5 lakh,
he would have paid Rs 4 lakh from his pocket.  What is the benefit of
taking insurance?  Therefore, remember a very simple rule
brother.  If you live in a metro city or a
big city, then you must have a minimum sum assured of ₹10 to ₹15 lakh.
And for this
you have to pay a premium of lakhs.
This does not happen every year, sir.   By
paying just ₹700 per month, you
get a cover of crores.
You get a very good cover in insurance.
I have given a link in the description for giving some ₹100.  If you click on that link, you will
get a separate discount.
You will be able to compare all the policies in detail there.
I am not promoting any one company,
brother.  I am not taking the name
of any company.  You can go there yourself by clicking on the link.
You will see which one is better and which one is not.  I am
telling you as many factors as I have, I will
tell you some more factors now.
Check all these factors in it.  Compare yourself.   Take whatever you
like.  To save some ₹700, a
person does not take medical insurance or even if he does, he takes the
cheaper one.
Due to which brother gets into additional trouble.
Ok?  So the rule is simple brother.   If it is
in metro cities then keep it at least 10 to 15 lakhs. If it is
in a small city then keep it at least 10 lakhs.
Now let's come to copayment.  The co-payment
which was written in my mother's case comment was 20%.
Now what does it mean to write payment to 20%
?  Understand carefully.
Copayment is such a thing that if it is written as 20%
then it means that the
person will pay 20% of the total bill himself. Whoever has the
policy will pay it, the hospital will pay only 80%.
If it is written as 30% then the
person will pay 30% himself and the hospital will pay only 70%.
If it is written as 50% then the
person will pay 50% himself and the hospital will
pay the remaining 50%. So, do you understand what happens? In
my mother's old policy, co-
payment was written as 20%, hence the
hospital did not pay 20%. We had to pay that 20%.
Thankfully, I had another
policy as well, I redeemed it from that,
otherwise I would have had to pay from my pocket.
Okay, now 20% copayment means that the
bill comes for ₹5 lakh, the insurance company
will say that we will pay ₹4 lakh and you will pay the remaining ₹1 lakh
yourself. So what is the best rule, should there be
zero copayment in your policy
or check it.  Whether it is written zero copayment or not,
10% max is acceptable.  Max to max
10% copayment is applicable.  But why should I take this also,
friend?  See what happens?  The
more your co-payment, whether it is 20%
co-payment or 30% co-payment, the
lower the insurance premium.  But if you take the comment as
zero then the insurance premium will be
higher.  Sir, but it is
worth paying higher insurance premium.  Because when
the time comes, the bill is in lakhs and the
difference in insurance premium is just ₹100.
Ok?
After that understand all the limits carefully.  There
is a policy of Rs 10 lakh.  The work will cost only ₹ lakh.
What happens?  There are many such policies
which have all the limits.
What will happen in that policy is that if you get knee
surgery done then there is a limit of Rs 3 lakh.   If you
undergo heart surgery, the limit is Rs 5 lakh.  If you get
this surgery done, this
is the limit.  Meaning, they will set a disease specific
limit.  Now no matter how much your policy is worth.
Now suppose
you or someone in your family needs to get knee replacement done and the
cost of knee replacement is ₹7 lakh, suppose
your policy is of ₹1 lakh or if it is a
policy of ₹10 lakh then the insurance company should pay the expense of ₹7 lakh
but why will it not pay, because
while taking the insurance you did not check whether there is a
sub limit in it, that is for knee
surgery there is a
sub limit of 3 lakh for knee replacement, there is a capping,
in case of knee replacement the
company will not give more than 3 lakh, so
despite having an insurance of 10 lakh, you will have to pay ₹4 lakh
from your own pocket.  Despite having insurance of Rs 10 lakh, the
company will give only Rs 3 lakh.  Ok?
So also check that there should not be any sub limit in your policy.
All limits should
be zero.  Ok?  After that
look at the waiting period.  What are multiple policies
?  It will tell you that the initial wait is 30 days.
Pre-existing disease: If someone already has a
disease, it will be covered after two-three years.   If there is
any contract cataract or hernia,
it will be covered after one to two years.
If there is maternity, it will be covered after two-three years.  Look, the
first thing is that whenever you buy any policy, do
not buy it after seeing it once.
You should always compare three or four policies.  And
you have to look at all these factors in three-four policies.
This factor also has to be seen.  There is a waiting
period.  It is there in every policy.
But you have to see that the waiting period should be
minimum.
You have to buy the policy which has the minimum waiting period.  There is a
waiting period in everything.
Nowadays such policies are available but
their premium is very high and there is
zero waiting period.  Meaning
everything is covered from day one.  Maternity is also covered.
But its premium is very high.  It is
not worth giving even that much.
You can take a little waiting period
depending on your physical condition.  But make
sure to cover which
company is offering the shortest waiting period in your premium.
Ok?
After that, the claim settlement ratio must be
seen.  Whichever company you want to
take the policy from, its claim settlement
ratio should be above 95%.
What is claim settlement ratio?
What percentage of claims has that company paid?
What percentage of claims have been rejected?
95% means that the company has passed more than 95% of the
claims.  Meaning he has given money to people.
Only 5% have been rejected.  Those could be
some reasons.  Ok?  So if it is above 95%
then that company is good.  Similarly,
taking health insurance from the company.  If it is 90 to 95 then it is
fine.  And if the
claim settlement ratio of any company is 85 or CSR,
then do not take the plan of such a company.  Ok?
Claim settlement ratio.  Well, you
can see all these pointers, you will click on the link I have given below
in the description.
You will compare.
You can see all these details of every company.  Just
give it some time.  There will also be the number of their executive.  You can
call him or even
give him a missed call.  As soon as you enter your number, you get a
call from there.  When you get a
call from there, ask him everything calmly.
Call him home and he will come to your home too.
He will explain it calmly without any money.
He will not charge any fees.  Will come to your home for free.  He
will explain it to you at home.
Will tell everything by comparing four plans.  These eight-nine options that I am telling you,
sorry not options, eight-nine
points that I am telling you,
ask him about each point.  And don't just
believe what he says.  He will say anything to sell it.
Ask him
where is the written word?  Show this, it should be written in that policy.
If you see all these things written then only
take it brother.  Ok?  So claim
settlement ratio followed by pre and post
hospitalization.
Sir, this is also very important.
Look at the hospital bill, it is not just a hospital bill.  The
doctor will prescribe some tests before admitting you to the hospital.  It costs money.  There is a
cost of medicines after discharge from the hospital.  There are expenses involved in that.
So have you taken such insurance
which covers the tests before the hospital
and also the cost of medicines after the hospital?  There should
be such a policy.
Ok?  Generally, you should look for such a policy in
which pre-hospitalization, that is,
whatever expenses are incurred for 60 to 90 days before the hospital,
medicines,
tests, waste, etc., should all be covered in that policy.
Well,
whatever expenses are incurred for 90 to 180 days after leaving the hospital,
all of them should be covered in that policy so that
you do not have to spend even a single rupee or any of your money.
You should see such a policy.  The pre
should cover 60 to 90 days.  Pre-
hospitalization and post-hospitalization should be
covered from 90 to 80 days, brother.  Correct?
After that point is Sir Restoration Benefit.
Nine out of 10 people make this mistake.
What happens?  Suppose I had to go to the hospital twice in a year.
Suppose one or
two members of the family have to leave.  Two, suppose
you do, what does restoration benefit say
?  As soon as the sum assured is over, suppose
a family member lost the policy, there was a policy of Rs 10 lakh
and the entire Rs 10 lakh was used up.  Now,
if another family
member has to go in the same year or you yourself have to
go for the second time, then there is no money left in your policy.
You paid the premium for one year.
You used Rs 10 lakh for that one year.
Now the policy is zero.  Now I will have to
pay all the money myself.  No.   There are
policies that
offer restoration benefits.  That means if the entire amount is
used then the company will restore the benefit in the same year.  This
means that the entire amount will be added
without charging you even ₹1.  So
you should look at the one with restoration benefits.  It gets
recharged automatically.
Full restoration is the best brother.  You
must check full restoration in your policy.  If it is
unlimited then there is a
bonus, that is, full restoration or
unlimited restoration, that means
four times, five times, 10 times, 15 times in a single year, as many times as you
finish the entire limit, it keeps getting added, that is what
we call unlimited
restoration or full restoration, once
yours is finished, they will pay it,
okay, you understood my point,
some questions, now come forward, now this is my last
message, I thought of writing it here,
I might say that
Sir, health insurance is not just a piece of paper.
This is the decision
you take today so that you do
n't have to appear weak in front of your family outside the hospital tomorrow.
When illness strikes,
savings are of no use because everything
is lost.  Neither does any investment work, it also gets
lost.  Only the right health
insurance is useful.  Therefore,
never buy a cheap policy.  Choose a policy that is strong and will
support you in your difficult times.   Does
not cost you money from your pocket.
If you buy the policy through the link we have given in the description, you
get a discount of 15 to 25%.
You can compare all the policies together.   The
number is given there.  You can call on the number
or as soon as you leave your number,
you will get a call there.  He will
guide you completely.  By paying just Rs 6700 per
month, you get coverage worth crores,
brother.  So save some money and
don't invite a big problem in the future.  Another thing in health insurance is
that some people
rely on corporate insurance thinking that we have got it
from our company.  Sir, do you
know what the biggest disadvantage is that the
day you lose your job, your insurance becomes
zero.  Because the
insurance from a corporate insurance company is
valid only as long as you are working in that company.
The day you lose your job and the next day you have to
go to the hospital,
God forbid, you will not get cover of even ₹1.  You will have to
pay not even a single rupee yourself and
until you get the next job and till you go to the next company, the
amount of policy cover is
not in your hands, it is
in the hands of the company, that is why getting corporate insurance is a
good thing but along with that, it is
very important to have your own personal health insurance.
People make foolish mistakes in taking health insurance, they get
greedy, they get
tempted to save a little money, due to which
when the time of hospitalization comes,
lakhs and crores of rupees of their land, property,
I have seen many people, everything gets ruined
because the hospital people have
no mercy in their hearts, sir, they have no affection for you,
your mother is admitted, father is admitted, brother is admitted,
wife is admitted, husband
is admitted, it does not matter to them, you are a
customer, only a customer,
their only thing is that they will treat you and
charge you and you will have to pay whatever the bill comes, it does
not matter whether
you have money or not, they will take it from
you and if you do not pay, they will not let your patient
leave the hospital
because for you he is a close friend
but for them, he is just a patient, just
a customer. That is why health insurance  Do
not be careless in taking it.
Take enough health insurance as per the pointers mentioned.
Make notes of all these pointers. Whenever that
executive from there calls you, then
ask him all these pointers,
how much cover is there for which thing and do
not leave out even a single pointer in these pointers
because
I have covered all these important ones.  Is it okay brother?  So that's it for today.
Health insurance
is very important brother.